Guide to the Joseph Hopkins Twichell Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Joseph Hopkins Twichell papers
1855-1918
YCAL MSS 755
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.72
(22 boxes)
Collection contains correspondence, writings, and personal and professional papers documenting the personal life and activities of Nineteenth- and early twentieth-century American pastor Joseph Hopkins Twichell. Correspondence consists of letters from Twichell, chiefly to his family, dating from 1855 to 1864, and incoming letters from Frederick Edwin Church, William Reed Eastman, and others. There are notebooks and scrapbooks dating from Twichell's service in the 71st New York Volunteers during the Civil War and later material, including journals, travel diaries, notebooks, scrapbooks, photograph albums, and drafts of sermons and speeches, document his personal and clerical activities.
Twichell, Joseph Hopkins, 1838-1918
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Joseph Twichell and Mrs. Charles Ives, 1951, and Charles P. Twichell and Mrs. Burton P. Twichell, 1967.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Joseph Hopkins Twichell (1838-1918)
Joseph Hopkins Twichell was born 27 May 1838 in Southington, Connecticut to Edward Twichell and Selina Delight Carter. He attended schools in Southington and graduated from Yale University with the class of 1859. He began his theological studies at Union Seminary in New York, but they were interrupted by the outbreak of the Civil War, during which he served as chaplain of the 71st New York Volunteers. After the war, he resumed his theological studies at Andover Theological Seminary and, in 1865, he took over as pastor of Asylum Hill Congregational Church in Hartford, Connecticut, where he remained until his death.
Biographical information taken from "Joseph Hopkins Twichell." Dictionary of American Biography. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1936. Biography In Contex t. Web. 21 June 2013.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, writings, and personal and professional papers documenting the life and activities of nineteenth and early twentieth century American pastor Joseph Hopkins Twichell. Correspondence consists of letters from Twichell, chiefly to his family, dating from 1855 to 1864, and incoming letters from Frederick Edwin Church, William Reed Eastman, and others. There are notebooks and scrapbooks dating from Twichell's service in the 71st New York Volunteers during the Civil War and later materials, including journals, travel diaries, notebooks, scrapbooks, photograph albums, and drafts of sermons and speeches, document his personal and clerical activities.
Arrangement
Organized into three groupings: May 1945 Acquisition, October 1967 Acquisition, and October 1967 Acquisition.
Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives; Clergy -- Connecticut -- Hartford; Congregational churches -- Sermons; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Photographic prints; Sermons -- Connecticut -- Hartford; Clergy -- New England -- 19th century; Church, Frederic Edwin, 1826-1900; Eastman, William Reed, 1835-1925; Twichell, Joseph Hopkins, 1838-1918; Asylum Hill Congregational Church (Hartford, Conn.); United States. Army. New York Volunteers, 71st
- May 1951 Acquisition, 1861-1918; 2.09; (6 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subdivisions, Journals and Civil War Letters, and arranged chronologically within each subdivision.
  Scope and Contents
  The May 1951 Acquisition consists of twelve autograph manuscript journals dating from 1874 through to 1918, and letters from Joseph Hopkins Twichell to his family and others. The journals also contain scattered clippings and letters.
  Former call number: Za Twichell.
  Gift of Joseph Twichell and Mrs. Charles Ives, 1951.
  - Journals
    - Volume 1, 1874-1875 (Box 1)
    - Volume 2, 1876-1877 (Box 1)
    - Volume 3, 1877-1879 (Box 1)
    - Volume 4, 1880-1882 (Box 1)
    - Volume 5, 1882-1888 (Box 1)
    - Volume 6, 1888-1898 (Box 2)
    - Volume 7, 1898-1903 (Box 2)
    - Volume 8, 1903-1907 (Box 2)
    - Volume 9, 1907-1913 (Box 3)
    - Volume 10, 1914 (Box 3)
    - Volume 11, 1915-1918 (Box 4)
      Entries dated from April 8, 1915 - April 13, 1915 are by Twichell; later entries are in an unidentified hand, possibly by Susan Twichell
    - Volume O: Various things that may be of interest to my children, undated (Box 4)
  - Civil War Letters
    - Letters, 1861-1864; 15 (Box 5)
    - Letters (copies), undated; 5 (Box 6)
- October 1967 Acquisition, 1855-1918; 4.59; (11 boxes)
  Organized into eight subdivisions: Civil War Material, Correspondence, Miscellaneous Material, Notebooks, Scrapbooks, Sermons, Speeches, and Travel Diaries.
  The October 1967 Acquisition contains Civil War material, correspondence, travel diaries, notebooks, scrapbooks, and drafts of sermons and speeches. Correspondence consists of letters from Twichell to his parents, dating from 1855 to 1861, and letters from others, including Frederick Edwin Church and William Reed Eastman.
  Gift of Charles P. Twichell and Mrs. Burton P. Twichell, 1967.
  - Civil War Material
    - "Diary of the Wilderness Campaign", 1864-1899; 2 (Box 7)
    - Notebooks, 1860-1864, undated; 4 (Box 7)
    - ["Memorabilia of the Civil War, Vol. I"?], scrapbook, 1861-1890, undated (Box 7)
    - "Memorabilia of the Civil War," scrapbooks, 1895-1914; 2 (Box 8)
      Includes Vols. II-III
  - Correspondence
    - "A" - "Z" general, 1858-1913, undated (Box 9)
    - Abelle, W. H., 1885-1886 (Box 9)
    - Boris, H. M., 1858-1866 (Box 9)
    - Carrington, Edward, 1858-1913, undated (Box 9)
    - Church, Frederick E., 1889 December 8 (Box 9)
    - Eastman, William R., 1864 February (Box 9)
    - Hawley, J. R., 1872-1895 (Box 9)
    - Hopkins, Henry, 1864-1869, undated; 2 (Box 9)
    - James, D. M., 1903 (Box 9)
    - Parker, E. P., 1870-1871, undated (Box 9)
    - Perkins, Edward, 1865-1866 (Box 9)
    - Rafferty, Thomas, 1862-1878, undated (Box 9)
    - Sickles, D. E., 1911, 1913 (Box 9)
    - Smith, Eugene, 1858-1873 (Box 9)
    - Stiles, Robert, 1860-1868, undated (Box 9)
    - Stiles, William A., 1863-1878, undated (Box 9)
    - Twichell, David C., 1918, undated (Box 9)
      Contains memorandum and copy of letter from S. Parkes Cadman
    - Twichell, Joseph Hopkins, 1867-1876, undated (Box 9)
    - Twichell, S. I., 1867, undated (Box 9)
    - Yung, Wing, 1874, 1881 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Material
    - Hartford in literature, 1911, undated; 2 (Box 9)
    - "The Pennsylvania Woods, 1856 & 1857", undated (Box 10)
    - Letters, 1855-1861; 6 (Box 10)
    - Unsorted material, 1885-1913, undated (Box 10)
  - Notebooks
    - "Contributions to the Gift of 125 Woodland Street", 1888, undated (Box 10)
    - "Parish Calls", 1868-1915; 2 (Box 10)
    - "Parish Calls", 1868-1915; 3 (Box 11)
    - "Sunday School Classes", 1880-1881; 2 (Box 11)
    - "Young People's Meetings", undated (Box 11)
    - Prayers, undated; 2 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbooks, v.0 - v.3, 1874-1901, undated; 4 (Box 12)
    - Scrapbooks, v.4 - v.6, 1901-1914, undated; 3 (Box 13)
    - Scrapbook, v.7, 1914-1915, undated (Box 14)
  - Sermons
    - "Acts 25: 18-19", undated (Box 14)
    - "The Coming Man", undated (Box 14)
    - "I Cor. XIV:3", undated (Box 14)
    - "I Cor. 16:9", undated (Box 14)
    - "Daniel I:17", undated (Box 14)
    - "Daniel X:12", undated (Box 14)
    - "Deut. 8:2", 1905 (Box 14)
    - "Eph. 4:28", 1905 (Box 14)
    - "Exodus III:5", undated (Box 14)
    - "Ezra 8:27", undated (Box 14)
    - "Gal I:11-12", 1876 (Box 14)
    - "Gal. I: 1-5: The Gospels View of Our Life", undated (Box 14)
    - " Hebrews XII: 22-24", 1898 September 25 (Box 14)
    - "Jeremiah 6:16", undated (Box 14)
    - "John 18:34", undated (Box 14)
    - "John 15:16", undated (Box 14)
    - "John 4:10", undated (Box 14)
    - "John VI:32-34", undated (Box 14)
    - "John IX:35-38", undated (Box 15)
    - "John XII:10-11", 1879 March 9 (Box 15)
    - "Livingstone", undated (Box 15)
    - "Luke II:51-52", undated (Box 15)
    - "Luke IV:16", undated (Box 15)
    - "Luke 12:23", 1908 (Box 15)
    - "Luke XVI:31", 1898 October 2[7?] (Box 15)
    - "Luke 22:61", undated (Box 15)
    - "Mark 6:6", undated (Box 15)
    - "Mark 10:17", undated (Box 15)
    - "Matt 6:28-30", undated (Box 15)
    - "Matt 8:9", 1896 October 19 (Box 15)
    - "Matt 9:16-17", undated (Box 15)
    - "Matt 10:34", undated (Box 15)
    - "I Pet. 4:12-14", undated (Box 15)
    - "Phil 2:9-11", 1905 (Box 15)
    - "Phil 3:12-14", 1895, 1904 (Box 15)
    - "Romans I:32", undated (Box 15)
    - "Romans XIV:21", undated (Box 15)
    - "I Sam XVII:37", undated (Box 15)
    - "2 Sam 3:1", undated (Box 15)
    - "2 Sam 3:38", undated (Box 15)
    - "I Tim 6:12", undated (Box 15)
    - "I Tim 6:17", undated (Box 15)
    - "II Tim I:5", undated (Box 15)
    - "Titus 2:9-10", 1893, 1901 (Box 15)
    - "What Is the Ministry For?", 1899, 1901 (Box 15)
  - Speeches
    Arranged alphabetically by venue and event.
    - Arbitration Treaty, 1897 February (Box 16)
    - Boston Yale Alumni, 1901 February 14 (Box 16)
    - Buffalo Yale Alumni Association, 1907 December 7 (Box 16)
    - Chicago Commercial Club, 1890 January (Box 16)
    - Civil and Religious Liberty, 1895 October 10 (Box 16)
    - Col. H. L. Higginson's Dinner to Yale and Harvard Football Teams, 1892 December 9 (Box 16)
    - The Confederate Apologia, undated (Box 16)
    - Dedication of President Woolsey's Statue, 1896 June 22 (Box 16)
    - Dedication of Soldiers' Monument at Andersonville, Ga., 1907 October 23 (Box 16)
    - Dedication of the Church of the Redeemer, 1906 December 12 (Box 16)
    - Dinner in Home of Walter Camp, 1892 February 26 (Box 16)
    - Dinner of New England Society, New York, 1902 December 22 (Box 16)
    - Dinner of the Boston Yale Alumni Association at Young's Hotel, 1891 February 3 (Box 16)
    - England's Change of Heart, undated (Box 16)
    - Fiction, Park Ch[urch], 1898 January 9 (Box 16)
    - First Baptist Ch[urch] Hartford, undated (Box 16)
    - Grant Memorial Service, 1885 August 8 (Box 16)
    - The Higher Criticism, 1902 (Box 16)
    - The Irishman as a Citizen and a Soldier, 1902 March 17 (Box 16)
    - The Joy of the Ministry, 1906 June (Box 16)
    - The Means of Grace, undated (Box 16)
    - New England Society, New York, 1891 December 22 (Box 16)
    - New York Harvard Club, 1897 February 19 (Box 16)
    - Opening of Yale Gymnasium, 1893 January 23 (Box 16)
    - Phi Beta Kappa Day, Harvard, 1891 June 25 (Box 16)
    - Society of Mayflower Descendants, New York, 1899 November 22 (Box 16)
    - The Soldierly Virtues, undated (Box 16)
    - Thirtieth Anniversary Talk, 1895 December 13 (Box 17)
    - Yale Alumni Asso[ciation], N.Y., 1898 February 14 (Box 17)
    - Yale Alumni Association of N.E. Pa, 1898 January 3 (Box 17)
    - Yale Alumni Dinner, New York, 1892 January 15 (Box 17)
    - Yale Alumni, Hartford, 1905 February (Box 17)
    - Yale Alumni Supper, NewYork, 1883 December 3 (Box 17)
    - Yale-Harvard Debate, 1892 March 25 (Box 17)
    - Yale-Harvard Football Dinner, New York, 189[9?] February (Box 17)
    - Yale-Princeton Debate, undated (Box 17)
  - Travel Diaries
    - "Excursion Abroad with A.C. Dunham and H. J. Johnson", 1871, 1877 (Box 17)
    - "Trip to Peru with Young Wing", 1874; 2 (Box 17)
    - "Abroad with the Spragues", 1899 (Box 17)
    - "Europe with [?] Jr. and A.C. Dunham", 1900 (Box 17)
    - "Vacation, 1905 (Pacific Coast)" (Box 17)
    - "England and Scotland (International Cong. Council)", 1908 (Box 17)
    - "Trip Abroad with E.P.P., May 31-July 15, 1910" (Box 17)
- October 1967 Acquisition, 1865-1917; 1.05; (5 boxes)
  Arranged in number order.
  The second October 1967 Acquisition contains five photograph albums.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 167.
  - Photograph album, volume 1, 1865-1890 (Box 18)
  - Photograph album, 1895-1910 (Box 19)
  - Photograph album, volume 3, 1890-1898 (Box 20)
  - Photograph album, volume 4, 1909-1914 (Box 21)
  - Photograph album, volume 5, 1915-1917 (Box 22)